now the last part about operating systems'
structures so if we look at the evolution
of operating systems over time we can observe
that things got more and more complicated
over time in the beginning operating systems
had a simple structure
or so-called monolithic structure there was
no dual mode so basically all applications
were directly interfacing with the
hardware for exchanging input or output of
course this makes everything vulnerable to
wrong or malicious code but this was just
the beginning of operating systems
so from simple structures we then moved to
the so-called layered approach it's a modular
approach in which you have these layers and
each layer maintains some data structure
or set of functions and routines it makes
it easier to debug because you
start having separate modules
the problem here is that of circular
references so you might want to have a module
that contains that CPU scheduler
and that would be above the module
of the processes because first you need
to define what a process is what a running program is
and that you can decide how you schedule them
but on the other hand you might want to
have the module about processes that stays above
the module about the CPU where you might have
also the scheduler because it's the process
who uses the CPU not the CPU who
uses the process
so it's hard to define and interconnect the
different modules if you need to keep them
in this layer one on top of the other with
exclusive competence in each layer so we then
moved to micro kernels the idea was to
keep the core part of the operating system
as small as possible and move everything that
is not
essential to the system to the user level program
it makes it smaller so it's also more easy
to maintain it and if you need to frequently
update the system / the user-level programs
this is also a good idea because you don't
need to recompile the entire kernel given that this model is
now external to the microkernel
it's also more secure because you run more
stuff in user mode so you have
a smaller set of portions of code that
are the ones that can actually run privileged instructions
so this makes it more secure
but of course it might suffer in performance
if you have to manage the file system
and every time you have to do something with
the disk you need to switch mode and give
control of that microkernel
you are wasting CPU cycles and this will affect
performance aside from microkernels you can
have modules the idea is similar but the difference is that you
can load the modules inside the kernel
either at boot time or on demand and this
is what's commonly done and it's still
done in the major operating systems we have today
and you don't need to recompile the kernel
that's the important thing and finally what
we actually have today is some kind of hybrid
system in which you take all the previous
ones or at least you pick parts of the previous one depending
on what let's say to try to take all the things
that were efficient depending on the case
and
the system that was developed before here you
just to have some examples so if you look
at Mac OS X you see that you have a layered
structure and then inside each layer you
can have different parts different modules
in the case of the OS X you have parts that
are from the unix system like sorry this one
and parts that have
been developed directly for OS X the
nice thing here with the layered structure
is that if you later on find out that you want
to reuse your operating system for example
to port it
to the iPhone as it was done in the beginning
when the first iPhone was
released then you can keep your core layers
and keep adding new layers on top of it so
for example a new layer that has to do with touch screen
that was not there before the iPhone
and again here I'm showing you the OS X case but
if you look at the android one it looks very similar
you have different layers and depending on
the layer then inside you have different
modules